Chapter 85.
The fountain.
that for 6,000 years, and no one knows how many millions of ages before, the
great whale should have been spouting all over the sea, and sprinkling and
mystifying the gardens of the deep, as with so many sprinkling or mystifying
pots, and that for some centuries back thousands of hunters should have been
close by the fountain of the whale, watching these sprinklings and
spoutings, that all this should be, and yet that down to this blessed minute, 15
and 1/4 minutes past 1:00 p.m. of this 16th day of December AD1 1851.
It should still remain a problem whether these spoutings are after all really
water or nothing but vapor. This is surely a noteworthy thing. Let us then
look at this matter along with some interesting items contingent. Everyone
knows that by the peculiar cunning of their gills, the Finey tribes in general
breathe the air which at all times is combined with the element in which they
swim. Hence, a herring or cod might live a century and never once raise its head
above the surface. But owing to his marked internal structure which gives
him regular lungs like a human being's, the whale can only live by inhaling the
disengaged air in the open atmosphere.
Wherefore the necessity for his periodical visits to the upper world,
but he cannot in any degree breathe through his mouth, for in his ordinary
attitude, the sperm whale's mouth is buried at least 8 ft beneath the
surface. And what is still more, his windpipe has no connection with his
mouth. No, he breathes through his spiracle alone, and this is on the top of his head.
If I say that in any creature breathing is only a function indispensable to
vitality, in as much as it withdraws from the air a certain element, which
being subsequently brought into contact with the blood, imparts to the blood its
vivifying principle, I do not think I shall heir, though I may possibly use
some superfluous scientific words.
Assume it, and it follows that if all the blood in a man could be airrated in
one breath, he might then seal up his nostrils and not fetch another for a
considerable time. That is to say, he would then live without breathing.
Anomalous as it may seem, this is precisely the case with the whale, who
systematically lives by intervals his full hour and more, when at the bottom,
without drawing a single breath, or so much as in any way inhaling a particle
of air, or remember, he has no gills.
How is this? Between his ribs and on each side of his spine, he is supplied
with a remarkable involved labyrinth of vermicelli-like vessels,
which vessels, when he quits the surface, are completely distended with
oxygenated blood, so that for an hour or more a thousand fathoms in the sea, he
carries a surplus stock of vitality in him, just as the camel crossing the
waterless desert carries a surplus supply of drink for future use in its
force. for supplementary stomachs. The anatomical fact of this labyrinth is
indisputable, and that the supposition founded upon it is reasonable and true,
seems the more cogent to me when I consider the otherwise inexplicable
obstinacy of that Leviathan in having his spoutings out, as the fishermen
phrase it. This is what I mean. If unmolested upon rising to the surface,
the sperm whale will continue there for a period of time exactly uniform with
all his other unmolested risings. Say he stays 11 minutes and jets 70 times, that
is respires 70 breaths, then whenever he rises again, he will be sure to have his
70 breaths all over again to a minute.
Now, if after he fetches a few breaths, you alarm him so that he sounds, he will
be always dodging up again to make good his regular allowance of air, and not
till those 70 breaths are told will he finally go down to stay out his full
term below. Remark, however, that in different individuals these rates are
different, but in any one they are alike. Now, why should the whale thus
insist upon having his spoutings out, unless it be to replenish his reservoir
of air, air descending for good? How obvious is it, too, that this necessity
for the whale's rising exposes him to all the fatal hazards of the chase. For
not by hook or by net could this vast leviathan be caught when sailing a
thousand fathoms beneath the sunlight.
Not so much thy skill then, oh hunter, as the great necessities that strike the victory to thee.
In man, breathing is incessantly going on, one breath only serving for two or
three pulsations, so that whatever other business he has to attend to, waking or
sleeping, breathe he must, or die he will. But the sperm whale only breathes
about 17th or Sunday of his time. It has been said that the whale only breathes
through his spout hole. If it could truthfully be added that his spouts are
mixed with water, then I appine we should be furnished with the reason why
his sense of smell seems obliterated in him. For the only thing about him that
at all answers to his nose is that identical spout hole, and being so
clogged with two elements, it could not be expected to have the power of
smelling. But owing to the mystery of the spout, whether it be water or
whether it be vapor, no absolute certainty can as yet be arrived at on
this head. Sure it is, nevertheless, that the sperm whale has no proper
alactories. But what does he want of them? No roses, no violets, no cologne water in the sea.
Furthermore, as his windpipe solely opens into the tube of his spouting
canal, and as that long canal, like the Grand Eerie canal, is furnished with a
sort of locks that open and shut for the downward retention of air or the upward
exclusion of water. Therefore, the whale has no voice, unless you insult him by
saying that when he so strangely rumbles, he talks through his nose. But
then again, what has the whale to say?
Seldom have I known any profound being that had anything to say to this world,
unless forced to stammer out something by way of getting a living. Oh, happy
that the world is such an excellent listener.
Now, the spouting canal of the sperm whale, chiefly intended, as it is, for
the conveyance of air, and for several feet laid along horizontally just
beneath the upper surface of his head, and a little to one side. This curious
canal is very much like a gas pipe laid
down in a city on one side of a street.
But the question returns whether this gas pipe is also a water pipe. In other
words, whether the spout of the sperm whale is the mere vapor of the exhaled
breath or whether that exhaled breath is mixed with water taken in at the mouth
and discharge through the spiracle. It is certain that the mouth indirectly
communicates with the spouting canal.
But it cannot be proved that this is for the purpose of discharging water through
the spiracle, because the greatest necessity for so doing would seem to be
when in feeding he accidentally takes in water. But the sperm whale's food is far
beneath the surface, and there he cannot spout even if he would. Besides, if you
regard him very closely and time him with your watch, you will find that when
unmolested, there is an undeviating rhyme between the periods of his jets
and the ordinary periods of respiration.
But why pester one with all this reasoning on the subject? Speak out. You
have seen him spout. Then declare what the spout is. Can you not tell water
from air? My dear sir, in this world it is not so easy to settle these plain
things. I have ever found your plain things the naughtiest of all. And as for
this whale spout, you might almost stand in it and yet be undecided as to what it
is precisely.
The central body of it is hidden in the snowy sparkling mist enveloping it. And
how can you certainly tell whether any water falls from it when always when you
are close enough to a whale to get a close view of his spout, he is in a
prodigious commotion, the water cascading all around him? And if at such
times you should think that you really perceive drops of moisture in the spout,
how do you know that they are not merely condensed from its vapor? Or how do you
know that they are not those identical drops superficially lodged in the spout
hole fisher which is counter sunk into the summit of the whale's head? For even
when tranquily swimming through the midday sea in a calm with his elevated
hump sundried as a dramadaries in the desert, even then the whale always
carries a small basin of water on his head, as under a blazing sun you will
sometimes see a cavity in a rock filled up with rain.
Nor is it at all prudent for the hunter to be over curious touching the precise
nature of the whale spout. It will not do for him to be peering into it and
putting his face in it. You cannot go with your pitcher to this fountain and
fill it and bring it away. For even when coming into slight contact with the
outer vapory shreds of the jet, which will often happen, your skin will
feverishly smart from the acridness of the thing so touching it. And I know one
who, coming into still closer contact with the spout, whether with some
scientific object in view or otherwise, I cannot say, the skin peeled off from
his cheek and arm. Wherefore among whalemen the spout is deemed poisonous.
They try to evade it. Another thing I have heard it said, and I do not much
doubt it, that if the jet is fairly spouted into your eyes, it will blind
you. The wisest thing the investigator can do then, it seems to me, is to let
this deadly spout alone.
Still, we can hypothesize, even if we cannot prove and establish. My
hypothesis is this, that the spout is nothing but missed, and besides other
reasons, to this conclusion I am impelled by considerations touching the
great inherent dignity and sublimity of the sperm whale. I account him no common
shallow being in as much as it is an undisputed fact that he is never found
on soundings or near shores. All other whales sometimes are. He is both
ponderous and profound. And I am convinced that from the heads of all
ponderous profound beings such as Plato, Piro, the devil, Jupiter, Dante, and so
on, there always goes up a certain semivvisible steam while in the act of
thinking deep thoughts. While composing a little treatise on eternity, I had the
curiosity to place a mirror before me, and he long saw reflected there, a
curious involved worming and undulation in the atmosphere over my head, the
invariable moisture of my hair, while plunged in deep thought after six cups
of hot tea in my thin shingled attic of an August noon. This seems an additional
argument for the above supposition.
And how nobly it raises our conceit of the mighty misty monster to behold him
solemnly sailing through a calm tropical sea. his vast mild head overhung by a
canopy of vapor, engendered by his incommunicable contemplations, and that
vapor, as you will sometimes see it, glorified by a rainbow, as if heaven
itself had put its seal upon his thoughts. For do you see, rainbows do
not visit the clear air. They only irradiate vapor. And so through all the
thick mists of the dim doubts in my mind, divine intuitions now and then
shoot, enkindling my fog with a heavenly ray. And for this I thank God for all
have doubts. Many deny, but doubts or denials. Few along with them have intuitions.
Doubts of all things earthly and intuitions of some things heavenly. This
combination makes neither believer nor infidel, but makes a man who regards
them both with equal eye.